Guide to the Robert H. "Ty" Robinson Papers 1896-2017
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Robert H. "Ty" Robinson Papers
1896-2017
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 926
Robinson, Robert H. (Ty), 1916-2018
1.0 linear feet
Robert H. (Ty) Robinson, a prominent member of the Missoula, Montana community, worked as a lawyer for many years, and volunteered with organizations that were proponents of education, health, and the environment. This collection consists of documents, ephemera, and photographs from Robinson's early life and education, his career, and his involvement in civic matters and organizations, including his historical talks.
Biographical Note
Robert H. "Ty" Robinson was born on January 25, 1916 in the town of Columbia Falls, Montana. Robinson's nickname "Ty" originated from a man Robinson's father had played baseball with: Ty Cobb. Ty Robinson was raised in six different towns from a young age, including Kalispell and Whitefish. He graduated from Flathead County High School in 1933, where he played basketball. In 1935, Robinson entered the University of Montana as an undergraduate student. From 1937-1939, Robinson played on the University of Montana Men's Basketball team. In 1940, Robinson graduated from the University of Montana with a Bachelor's degree in history and political science.
After graduating from the University of Montana, Robinson worked for the Department of Justice, slowly working his way up the ranks. He entered the military in 1943, and served until 1946 as "commissioned on staff" and commander on the Service Force Pacific Fleet in the U.S. Navy. Upon completion of service in 1946, Robinson returned to the University of Montana, where he graduated with his Juris Doctor degree in 1948. After graduating in 1948, Robinson was admitted into practice in the same year, then entering the Missoula Mercantile work force as in-house counsel. Starting in 1950, Robinson taught in the University of Montana School of Business and Business Law for 11 years. In 1954, Robinson became a partner in the law firm, Garlington, Lohn, and Robinson, from which he retired in 1987 to become "of counsel." In 1971, Robinson was sworn in by the Montana Supreme Court to the Montana Constitutional Convention Commission.
Robinson was an active member of the Montana community, serving on boards and civic councils with a range of missions. Some of Robinson's contributions include serving as a past president of the Missoula Rotary Club, a member of the Missoula Chamber of Commerce, a member of the Community Medical Center Foundation, and a past president of the Western Montana Council of Boy Scouts. Robinson was active in civil affairs on the state, county, and city levels, where his focus was on education, health, and the environment.
Robinson married his wife, Jean E. Fritz, on November 23, 1939, and had two children, John and Laird. Ty Robinson died in Missoula March 27, 2018 at the age of 102.
The Robert H. (Ty) Robinson papers cover the date range 1896-2017. This collection includes school records, records from the Missoula Mercantile, various documents from organizations Robinson was involved in as a board member or volunteer, historic photographs of Missoula, and documents and ephemera from his time supporting and volunteering with the Boy Scouts. Materials in this collection were originally housed in binders labeled, "Miscellaneous memories to go through later," "Ty's Memory Book," and "The Merc."
The materials in this collection have been arranged in to five series:
Series I: Life and Education, 1922-2016, 0.2 linear feet
Series II: Career, 1944-2014, 0.3 linear feet
Series III: Organizations and Civic Involvement, 1930-2017, 0.5 linear feet
Series IV: Historic Photographs, 1896-1910, 6 photographs
Series V: Audio Visual Materials, 2000s-2010s
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
This material was held by Ty Robinson before being donated to the Archives.
The majority of material in this collection was donated to the University of Montana's Archives and Special Collections by Ty Robinson's friend Jari Davis, with permission from Robinson's family. Recorded talks were donated by Robinson's friend James Habeck in 2005 and 2011.
Copies of Ty Robinson's recorded interviews, as well as verbatim transcripts of those interviews, are available as Oral History Collection OH 270-038, OH 270-039, OH 396-008, and OH 415-001 from the K. Ross Toole Archives.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Robinson, Robert H., 1916-2018--Archives
Missoula Mercantile Company; Boy Scouts of America. Western Montana Council
Community development--Montana--Missoula; Social participation--Montana--Missoula; Missoula (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Missoula; Montana
Lawyers--Montana--Missoula; Civic leaders--Montana--Missoula
- Life and Education, 1922-2016; Series I; 0.2 linear feet
  This series is arranged chronologically by date of event in Robinson's life.
  - Ty Robinson Early Life, circa 1920s, 1923 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Ty Robinson School Records, 1922-1927 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Montana DeMolay, 1937 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Navy, 1950 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1953-1985 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Law Degree, 1970 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1979 and 1982 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Christmas Correspondence, 1990-2009 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Ty's Memory Book, 2011; Memory book was originally housed in a binder and created by Robinson's friend Jim Habeck (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Ty's Memory Book Photographs, 2011; Memory book was originally housed in a binder and created by Robinson's friend Jim Habeck (Box-folder 1/11)
  - R.H. Robinson: Life History, Circa 2016 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Career, 1944-2014; Series II; 0.3 linear feet
  This series is arranged by order of career, then chronologically by category.
  - Supreme Court Certificate to Practice Law, 1948 (Box-folder OS 1/1)
  - Mercantile Correspondence, 1944 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Mercantile Name License, 1953 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - The Mercantile: Documents and Policies, 1953 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - History of the Mercantile, 1976 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Notes on the Mercantile, Circa 1980s (Box-folder 1/17)
  - History of the Mercantile Newspaper Article, 2008 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Missoula Mercantile: Robinson and McLeod Interview, 2011 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Circa 1965-1970s (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Senate Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Garlington, Lohn, and Robinson Law Firm, 2014 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Interviews with R.H. (Ty) Robinson, 2005-2011 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Talks and Speeches by Ty Robinson, 2005-2011 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Missoulian Interviews, 2012 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-1990s (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Robinson Calendar, 2001; Calendar contains many notes from Robinson (Box-folder OS 1/2)
  - Photographs, Circa 1970s-2010s (Box-folder 1/27)
- Organizations and Civic Involvement, 1930-2017; Series III; 0.5 linear feet
  This series is arranged alphabetically, then chronologically by category.
  - Boy Scouts Ephemera, 1930-2010; Contains Robinson's original Boy Scout Cap from Camp Jefferson in 1930 and BSA patch from 2003 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Boy Scouts Meeting Documents, 1951 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Boy Scouts Meeting Documents, 1952 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Boy Scouts Meeting Documents, 1953 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Boy Scouts Meeting Documents, 1954 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Boy Scouts Poster, 1954 (Box-folder OS 1/3)
  - Boy Scouts Silver Beaver Award, 1960 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Boy Scots Silver Beaver Certificate, 1960 (Box-folder OS 1/4)
  - Scouting Legacy Award, 2010 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Eagle Court of Honor Ceremony, 2015 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Community Medical Center, 1989-2016 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Disabled Veterans National Foundation, 1980 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Leadership Missoula, 2007 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Legacy Montana, Circa 2010s (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Montana Massoinic Foundation, 1977 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Rotary, Circa 2017 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Rotary: Paul Harris Fellow Certificate of Appreciation, 2017 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Sportsman of the Year, 1980 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - University of Montana Charter Day, 2011 (Box-folder 2/17)
- Historic Photographs, 1896-1910; Series IV; 6 photographs
  This series is arranged by photograph number.
  - View of Missoula, Montana, from Waterworks Hill, circa 1910 (Photo number 87-0001)
  - View of Missoula, Montana, from Waterworks Hill, 1896 (Photo number 87-0002)
  - View of Missoula, Montana, from Waterworks Hill, circa 1910 (Photo number 87-0003)
  - View of Island and South Missoula from the Higgins building, circa 1900 (Photo number 87-0004)
  - View of Higgins Bridge, the Clark Fork River, and south Missoula during the flood of 1908; taken from top of First National Bank Building (Photo number 87-0005)
  - View of Higgins Bridge, the Clark Fork River, and south Missoula during the flood of 1908; taken from top of First National Bank Building (Photo number 87-0006)
- Audiovisual Media, circa 2000s-2010s; Series V; 0.1 linear foot
  This series is currently unprocessed.
  - unprocessed audiovisual media, circa 2000s-2010s (Box 3)